<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/document.dtd">

<!--
 * Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
 

<s1 title="Command line options for &xslt4jc-short;">
<ul>
<li><link anchor="options">Options</link></li>
<li><link anchor="examples">Examples</link></li>
<li><link anchor="faq">Simple FAQs</link></li>
<li><link anchor="trax">Using options from the JAXP transform APIs</link></li>
</ul>
   
<anchor name="options"/>
<s2 title="Options">
<p>The <code>org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process</code> command line now supports &xslt4jc-short; for transformation. 
You can use the new <code>-XSLTC</code> option to enable the &xslt4jc-short; support.</p> 
<p>The following existing options can be used with -XSLTC:</p>
<p><code>-IN, -XSL, -OUT, -V, -EDUMP, -XML, -TEXT, -HTML, -PARAM, <br/>
-MEDIA, -FLAVOR, -DIAG, -URIRESOLVER, -ENTITYRESOLVER,<br/>
-CONTENTHANDLER</code></p>

<p>The following existing options do not work with <code>-XSLTC</code>. If any of them is used 
with <code>-XSLTC</code>, a message is printed and the option is ignored.</p>
<p><code>-QC, -TT, -TG, -TS, -TTC, -TCLASS, -L, -INCREMENTAL, <br/>
-NOOPTIMIMIZE, -RL</code></p>

<p>We also have a new set of options for <code>-XSLTC</code>. They are all two letter options. The first 
letter is X and the second letter is the same as the corresponding option in the &xslt4jc-short; command line 
<code>org.apache.xalan.xsltc.cmdline.Compile</code>.</p>

<p>These new options can only be used with <code>-XSLTC</code>. If any of them is used
with &xslt4ji;, a message is printed and the option is ignored.</p>

<p>Here is the list of the new options:</p>
<ul>
  <li><code>-XO [optional translet_name]</code><br/>
  Assign the name to the generated translet. If the translet_name is omitted, the translet is 
  generated using the default name (same as the xsl).</li>
  <li><code>-XD destination_directory</code><br/>
  Specify a destination directory for translet. The generated translet classes will be put 
  under the specified destination directory.</li>
  <li><code>-XJ jar_name</code><br/>
  Package translet classes into a jar file of name &lt;jar_name&gt;</li>
  <li><code>-XP package_name</code><br/>
  Specify a package name prefix for all generated translet classes</li>
  <li><code>-XN</code><br/>
  Enable XSL template inlining into one big method</li>
  <li><code>-XX</code><br/>
  Turn on additional debugging message output</li>
  <li><code>-XT</code><br/>
  Use translet to transform if possible</li>
</ul>
<note>The translet name is the same as the name of the Java class that
implements the translet.  If the name specified by the <code>-XO</code> option
or derived from the URL for the stylesheet contains characters that are not
permitted in a Java class name, any such character will be replaced with an
underscore.  For example, if the translet name specified by the <code>-XO</code>
option is <code>my-stylesheet</code>, or if the URL of the stylesheet is
<code>http://example.org/my-stylesheet.xsl</code>, the translet will actually
be named<code>my_stylesheet</code>.
</note>
</s2>

<anchor name="examples"/>
<s2 title="Examples">

<p>You can just add the <code>-XSLTC</code> option to your existing option list so that it will do 
the same thing as before, but using &xslt4jc-short;.</p>

<p>Here is a simple example on how to use &xslt4jc-short;:</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -in test.xml -xsl test.xsl -xsltc</code></p>
<p>&xslt4jc-short; compiles the stylesheet on the fly and uses the bytecode in memory to transform the input xml. 
No translet class is generated in this simple usage pattern.</p>
<p>If you want to generate translet classes from the stylesheet, you can use the <code>-XO</code> option:</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -in test.xml -xsl test.xsl -xsltc -xo</code></p>

<p>This example still uses the stylesheet for transformation, but it also generates the 
translet class "test.class".</p>

<p>You can use the <code>-XJ, -XP</code> or <code>-XD</code> options to further customize the translet 
generation behavior. Translets will be generated if any of the options <code>-XO, -XJ</code> or 
<code>-XT</code> is used.</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -in test.xml -xsl test.xsl -xsltc -xo newTranslet -xd temp -xp org.apache.test -xj translets.jar</code></p>

<p>The above command line uses the xsl for transformation. It also generates translet classes in
the name of <code>newTranslet</code>, using a package prefix of <code>org.apache.test</code>, and packages the translets
into the jar file <code>translets.jar</code> under the <code>temp</code> directory.</p>

<p>All of the examples above use the stylesheet to do the transformation. If the translets are 
already generated, you can use the <code>-XT</code> option to specify that you want to use the existing translets for transformation. 
The <code>-XT</code> option has a makefile like feature in that it will compare the timestamps of the translet 
and the stylesheet. If the translet is newer, it is used for the transformation, otherwise the stylesheet is 
used and the translet is regenerated.</p>

<p>The translet is loaded from the specified destination directory or the current directory, using
the specified translet name or the xsl base name, depending on whether the <code>-XD</code> or 
<code>-XO</code> option is used. The options <code>-XO, -XD, -XP</code> and <code>-XJ</code>
can be used with the <code>-XT</code> option to tell &xslt4jc-short; how to find the translet classes. The translets
are directly read in as bytecode. You do not need to add the translet directory or the jar file to your
classpath.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -in test.xml -xsl test.xsl -xsltc -xt -xj translets.jar -xd temp</code></p>

<p>This command line will search for the translet <code>test.class</code> inside the jar file <code>temp/translets.jar</code>. If it is 
found and newer than test.xsl, it is used for the transformation; otherwise the xsl is used and the
translet is generated and packaged in the same jar.</p>

<p>Here is how the makefile feature for the <code>-XT</code> option works:</p>
<ol>
  <li>If the xsl does not exist, use the translet</li>
  <li>If the translet does not exist, use the xsl and generate a new translet</li>
  <li>If both exist and the translet is newer, use the translet for transformation</li>
  <li>If both exist and the xsl is newer, use the xsl for transformation and regenerate the translet</li>
</ol>
</s2>

<anchor name="faq"/>
<s2 title="Simple FAQs">

<p><em>Q:</em> If I use the <code>-XT</code> option, how can I tell if it is using the translet or the stylesheet for transformation?</p>
<p><em>A:</em> Use the <code>-XX</code> option. When &xslt4jc-short; uses the translet for transformation, you will see a debug 
message like "Tranform using translet ..." or "Tranform using translet ... from jar file ...".</p>

<p><em>Q:</em> I want to use a translet for transformation, and I don't have the stylesheet.</p>
<p><em>A:</em> Suppose the translet class is <code>c:\translets\myTranslet.class</code>, you can use the following command line:</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -in test.xml -xsltc -xt -xo myTranslet -xd c:\translets</code></p>
<p>If you use <code>-XT</code> option, the <code>-XSL</code> option can be omitted. You have to specify the translet name 
using the <code>-XO</code> option because there is no default translet name in this situation.</p>

<p><em>Q:</em> I only want to compile the stylesheet. I don't want to do a transformation.</p>
<p><em>A:</em> JAXP has no notion of compiling a stylesheet. However, you can achieve the same effect by 
running a dummy transformation and tell &xslt4jc-short; to save the translet class. Example:</p>
<p>&gt; <code>java org.apache.xalan.xslt.Process -xsl test.xsl -xsltc <br/>-xo</code></p>
<p>This command runs a transformation on an empty input and generates the translet <code>test.class</code>.</p>
</s2>

<anchor name="trax"/>
<s2 title="Using options from the JAXP transform APIs">
<p>You can use some of the attributes in the <code>TransformerFactoryImpl</code> class of &xslt4jc-short; to 
customize the translet behaviors from JAXP.</p>

<p>Here is the list of attributes in <code>org.apache.xalan.xsltc.trax.TransformerFactoryImpl</code> 
and their corresponding Process command line options:</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td><em>Attributes</em></td>
    <td><em>Process command line options</em></td>
    <td><em>Default values</em></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>translet-name</td>
    <td>-XO</td>
    <td>GregorSamsa</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>destination-directory</td>
    <td>-XD</td>
    <td>null</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>package-name</td>
    <td>-XP</td>
    <td>null</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>jar-name</td>
    <td>-XJ</td>
    <td>null</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>generate-translet</td>
    <td></td>
    <td>false</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>auto-translet</td>
    <td>-XT</td>
    <td>false</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>use-classpath</td>
    <td></td>
    <td>false</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>enable-inlining</td>
    <td>-XN</td>
    <td>false</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>debug</td>
    <td>-XX</td>
    <td>false</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>You can set the attributes using the JAXP interface <code>TransformerFactory.setAttribute(String name, Object value)</code>. 
The four attributes <code>translet-name, destination-directory, package-name and jar-name</code> are transient. 
They only apply to the next <code>newTemplates()</code> or <code>newTransformer()</code> call. Their values are reset to 
the default after the call.</p>

<p>The <code>generate-translet</code> attribute does not have a corresponding command line option. This attribute is
implied when the <code>-XO</code> or <code>-XJ</code> option is used. The purpose is to make the command line
usage syntax a little bit simpler. Setting the <code>generate-attribute</code> attribute to true from JAXP is 
equivalent to using the <code>-XO</code> option without the optional translet name from the Process command line.</p>

<p>If the <code>use-classpath</code> attribute is set to <code>true</code>, the translet will be loaded
from the <code>CLASSPATH</code>. This attribute is typically used in a case when the translets are packaged in a 
prebuilt jar file which is included in the <code>CLASSPATH</code>. You can set the <code>translet-name</code> attribute 
to indicate which translet to use. If this attribute is not set, the name of the translet is taken from 
the base name of the stylesheet. The <code>jar-name</code> attribute is not used in this situation.</p>

<p>The following example shows you how to do the same thing from JAXP for the question 2 in the FAQ.</p>

<source>
// set the system property javax.xml.transform.TransformerFactory in order to use &xslt4jc-short;
String key = "javax.xml.transform.TransformerFactory";
String value = "org.apache.xalan.xsltc.trax.TransformerFactoryImpl";
Properties props = System.getProperties();
props.put(key, value);
System.setProperties(props);

TransformerFactory tfactory = null;
try {
  tfactory = TransformerFactory.newInstance();
}
catch (TransformerFactoryConfigurationError pfe) { pfe.printStackTrace(); }

// set the translet name
tfactory.setAttribute("translet-name", "myTranslet");

// set the destination directory
tfactory.setAttribute("destination-directory", "c:\\translets");

// use the translet for transformation if possible
tfactory.setAttribute("auto-translet", "true");

// You can create a Templates object from an empty Source if the translet is specified.
Templates templates = tfactory.newTemplates(new StreamSource());
</source>
</s2>
</s1>
