<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE s1 SYSTEM "../../style/dtd/document.dtd">
<!--
 * Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
 
<!-- apologies in advance for the brief writing style! -sc -->

<s1 title="&xslt4j; Release builds">
<ul>
<li><link anchor="intro">Introduction</link></li>
<li><link anchor="developers">Developer Guidelines</link></li>
<li><link anchor="builds">Running Product Builds - Overview</link></li>
<li><link anchor="builds2">Running Product Builds - Details</link></li>
</ul>


<anchor name="intro"/>
<s2 title="Introduction">
  <p>
    This page is <em>not</em> for users
    who want to download pre-built jars of &xslt4j; or download 
    the source code for &xslt4j; and build from that.
    Users who want to do that 
    should see the <link idref="downloads">Download/Build</link> page.
  </p>
  <p>
    This page is intended for Xalan committers and developers and is about the 
    process to create a new release. It
    provides a selection of brief checklists for committers and developers 
    about build procedures for the &xslt4j; community.  Community input 
    is appreciated; if you have questions, please ask on
    <link idref="contact_us">xalan-dev</link>.
  </p> 
  <p>
    <note>The product build related sections of this document are still 
    quite thin - they're mainly bullet points almost in checklist style.  
    If you don't fully understand the procedures in this document, then 
    you probably should ask for help first!
    </note> 
  </p>
  
</s2>


<anchor name="developers"/>
<s2 title="Developer Guidelines">
<note>This section is meant to become a set of guidelines for all &xslt4j;
committers and developers who wish to submit patches.  It's still in progress; 
suggestions to xalan-dev@xml.apache.org appreciated.</note> 
  <p>The project's technical mailing list for all committers and developers 
  interested in the API and inner workings is 
  <jump href="mailto:xalan-dev@xml.apache.org">xalan-dev@xml.apache.org</jump>; 
  it's a good idea to 
  <link idref="contact_us" anchor="dev-mailing-list">subscribe</link>
  if you plan to work on &xslt4j;.  Logs of all Subversion 
  commits are automatically sent to <jump href="mailto:xalan-cvs@xml.apache.org">xalan-cvs@xml.apache.org</jump>, although 
  discussions should happen on xalan-dev.  You can read more <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">about mailing lists.</jump></p>
  <p>&xslt4j; is a fairly mature project; one where most committers and many 
  users expect that the daily build will be mostly functional.  Very risky changes 
  or major architecture updates should be discussed ahead of time or committed onto 
  branches.</p> 
  <p>Developers should always run the Smoketest before checking in files or 
  submitting patches to the list.  If the Smoketest does not pass, you should 
  either fix whatever you broke or get consensus from xalan-dev that 
  it's OK to break the Smoketest temporarily.  The Smoketest is a selection of 
  API functionality tests and a pass through a wide variety of XSLT conformance 
  tests that ensure basic functionality.  You can also read a full set of 
  <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/test/overview.html">documentation about the tests</jump>.</p>
  <p>
  (Smoketest doc is TBD!)
<source>cvs co xml-xalan/java xml-xalan/test
cd xml-xalan/java
build smoketest
# Ant build will fail if smoketest fails.
</source>
</p>
</s2>

<anchor name="builds"/>
<s2 title="Running Product Builds - Overview">
<p>Official builds of &xslt4j; require a few more steps than simply doing 
'build fulldist'.  This is a quick checklist of the steps; if you are 
not comfortable following this list, then please seek help on xalan-dev.</p> 

<s3 title="Release Types">
<p>Official builds come in several flavors:</p>
<ul>
<li>Major version releases: when significant new or changed functionality comes out, 
we bump up the major build number; i.e. from 2.3 to 3.0.  This is fairly rare; 
anyone reading xalan-dev will know when this is happening.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Minor version releases happen when we fix bugs or make moderate improvements to 
the product.  These are moving from 2.3 to 2.4; they should be planned out.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Maintenance point releases are when we find bugs in an existing version and fix them without 
adding new functionality; these go from 2.3 to 2.3.1.  They should be done on a 
branch if the mainline development has already moved forward; the point is to 
make critical bugfixes for existing customers who want to stay on the stable release.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Developer releases are very ad hoc; they represent a chunk of progress along the 
HEAD of our CVS tree towards a new major or minor release. The developer release 
versions would be going from 2.3 to a new 2.4.D1 - the developer release is somewhat 
like a 'beta' towards a new 2.4 minor version release.  Quality standards for developer 
releases are much less stringent than other releases.<br/><br/></li>
</ul>
</s3>

<s3 title="Condensed Build Checklist">
<p>A very brief list of stages in running a build.</p>
<ol>
<li>Email xalan-dev with build plan.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Verify all code changes are checked in.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Verify any doc updates for code changes are in.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Update build numbers in doc, code, and build scripts.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Do a clean checkout and tag the sources.<br/><br/></li>
<li>build fulldist -logfile ..\fulldist.log<br/><br/></li>
<li>build fulldist-separatejars -logfile ..\fulldist-separatejars.log<br/><br/></li>
<li>Run the smoketest for Xalan Interpretive and XSLTC.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Verify smoketest passed; check docs built with new build numbers.<br/><br/></li>
<li>PGP/GPG sign all .zip/.tar.gz distribution files (distros).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Copy distros up to the website.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Update website documentation set.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Email xalan-dev with build notice!<br/><br/></li>
</ol>
</s3>

</s2>

<anchor name="builds2"/>
<s2 title="Running Product Builds - Details">
<p>This section is still in progress, but should have all the basics. 
You should already have read the <link anchor="builds">build overview</link> above and you should already be 
familiar with our build.xml script and development processes.</p> 

<s3 title="Pre-Build Steps">
<p>Preparation before you run a build.</p>
<ul><!-- I'd prefer to use ol's, but the start="num" attr isn't supported in Stylebook -->
<li>Email xalan-dev with build plan.</li>
</ul>
<p>Apache projects are communities: you should always let the community know what 
the plans for builds are.  The xalan-dev mailing list is the primary communication 
mechanisim for committers and developers working on &xslt4j;; you may also wish 
to cc: the xalan-j-users list to let other users and folks know what's coming. 
For major releases you may also want to cc: the general@xml.apache.org list so that 
other xml.apache.org projects know our plans, although this is not required.</p>
<ul>
<li>Verify all code changes are checked in.</li>
</ul>
<p>Ensure that any code changes you're planning to have in this release are actually 
checked in; make sure any open work by other committers is in a stable state. 
You should also review any other projects we're dependent on and make sure 
that (when possible) we've updated to the latest version of their .jar files: 
like <code>xercesImpl.jar</code>, <code>ant.jar</code>, etc.  Note that occasionally we will have a specific 
development need to stay with a different version of these projects.</p>
</s3>

<s3 title="Updating Doc And Version Numbers">
<p>Getting documentation and version numbers in sync.</p>
<ul>
<li>Verify any doc updates for code changes are in.</li>
</ul>
<p>Check that the documentation is up to date.  Make sure that any new 
features or major functionality changes are properly documented.</p>
<p>Update the commits list and the 'what was done' list in xdocs/sources/xalan/readme.xml 
and whatsnew.xml.  Note that currently some of the status information for the 
&xslt4jc-short; portion of &xslt4j; is stored separately in xsltc_history.xml and XSLTCDONE
</p>
<p>Check in all your work!</p>

<ul>
<li>Update build numbers in doc, code, and build scripts.</li>
</ul>
<p>Once you know what the version number should be, you'll need to update 
it in a number of places - both for the product itself, for the build 
system, and for the documentation.  If you don't understand how to update 
any of these files, then please get help - <b>don't</b> just try to wing it.</p>
<ul>
<li>build.xml 
Update the following lines for each version field:<br/>
&lt;property name="version.VERSION" value="2"/><br/>
&lt;property name="version.RELEASE" value="7"/><br/>
&lt;property name="version.DEVELOPER" value=""/><br/>
&lt;property name="version.MINOR" value="0"/><br/>
&lt;property name="parser.version.VERSION" value="2"/><br/>
&lt;property name="parser.version.RELEASE" value="7"/><br/>
&lt;property name="parser.version.MINOR" value="1"/><br/>
<br/></li>
<li>xml-xalan/java/xdocs/sources/xalan-jsite (document id="index" label="Xalan-Java x.x")<br/><br/></li>
<li>If you updated <code>xercesImpl.jar</code> or <code>xml-apis.jar</code>, add a new entry in
xml-xalan/java/src/org/apache/xalan/xslt/EnvironmentCheck.java</li>
</ul>
<p>I did remind you to check in all your work, didn't I?</p>
</s3>


<s3 title="Run A Candidate Distribution Build">
<p>Get clean sources and build a distribution and (at least) the smoketest.</p>
<ul>
<li>Do a clean checkout and tag the sources.</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, you checked in all your earlier work to the CVS repository, right?</p>
<p>The safest way to perform a build for distribution is to check out a fresh 
new copy of the repository from CVS.  This avoids any potential problems with 
uncommitted changes or extra files on your local machine.</p>
<p>Check out a new copy of both xml-xalan/java and xml-xalan/test repositories 
to a blank directory on your local machine.  You then need to tag the files in 
the repository with a marker noting that these versions are the actual ones 
being used in the build (you could actually do this after running the build below). 
Use the CVS tag command to add the tag to both repositories (/java and /test). 
The tag name should be something like 'xalan-j_2_4'; look at the log of any file 
to see the exact format of previous builds.</p>


<ul>
<li>build fulldist site -logfile ..\fulldist.log</li>
</ul>
<p>The above command will build the binary and source distribution .zip/.tar.gz 
files, in which the Xalan Interpretive and Xalan Compiled (XSLTC) processors
are combined into the <code>xalan.jar</code> file.  All the samples and the documentation
are built as well. The log of the build is saved in ..\fulldist.log.  Note 
that this will take up a moderate amount of space, especially when building 
the .tar.gz files, so ensure you have plenty of disk space first.</p>
<p>Review the fulldist.log file quickly to ensure there were no build errors.   
Note that you can ignore any 'warnings' from the javadoc target; however any 
'error's in the documentation must be fixed.</p>

<ul>
<li>build fulldist-separatejars site -logfile ..\fulldist-separatejars.log</li>
</ul>
<p>Before running this command, rename the generated <strong>./build</strong> directory from 
the 'fulldist' command above to another name, for example, build-combinedjar.  The 
'fulldist-separatejars' command will build the binary and source distribution 
.zip/.tar.gz files, in which the Xalan Interpretive and Xalan Compiled (XSLTC) processors
are built into separate jars; <code>xalan.jar</code> and <code>xsltc.jar</code> respectively.  All the samples and 
the documentation are built as well.  The log of the build is saved in ..\fulldist-separatejars.log.
Note that this will take up a moderate amount of space, especially when building the .tar.gz 
files, so ensure you have plenty of disk space first.</p>
<p>Review the fulldist-separatejars.log file quickly to ensure there were no build errors.   
Note that you can ignore any 'warnings' from the javadoc target; however any 
'error's in the documentation must be fixed.</p>
<p>The results of the build will be
placed in the ./build directory.  Rename the xalan-j_2_x_x-bin.zip and xalan-j_2_x_x-bin.tar.gz
files to xalan-j_2_x_x-bin-2jars.zip and xalan-j_2_x_x-bin-2jars.tar.gz respectively so that 
this binary distribution can be distinguished from the binary distributions created by the
'fulldist' target.  The source distributions, xalan-j_2_x_x-src.zip and xalan-j_2_x_x-src.tar.gz
are duplicates of those created by the 'fulldist' target.</p>

<ul>
<li>Run the smoketest for Xalan Interpretive and XSLTC.</li>
</ul>
<p>Change to the xml-xalan\test directory and build the test harness by entering
"build jar -logfile jar.log".  Run the smoketest for the Xalan Interpretive processor by
entering "build smoketest -logfile smoketest.log". Run the smoketest for the XSLTC by
entering "build smoketest.xsltc -logfile smoketest.xsltc.log". 
</p>

<ul>
<li>Verify smoketest passed; check docs built with new build numbers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Review the smoketest.log and smoketest.xsltc.log files.  If they do not say
that the Smoketest passed, then you must fix the test results before 
posting the build.  Even for developer's builds, we must ensure that at least 
the Smoketest passes.  For major or minor releases, we should also perform more 
testing to ensure stability.  More detailed log files for the Smoketest can 
be found in the xml-xalan/test/smoketest/ directory.</p>
<p>You should also test that the documentation built properly, and that it 
has the proper build or release number that you edited above.</p>
<p>IMPORTANT: if you changed any files at all, be sure to check in your work 
and re-start this process!</p>

</s3>

<s3 title="Code Signing and Posting">
<p>Sign the distribution units so end-users can trust them, then copy to the website.</p>
<ul>
<li>PGP/GPG sign all .zip/.tar.gz distribution files (distros).</li>
</ul>
<p>As a security measure, all xml.apache.org projects must sign or otherwise 
ensure the integrity of their public distributions.  This is most commonly done 
by signing the actual .zip/.tar.gz files with your personal PGP or GPG key. 
Note that you must sign the files before copying them up to the website.</p>
<p>The Xalan Java distributions consist of: the source distribution files 
(xalan-j_x_x_x-src.zip and xalan-j_x_x_x-src.tar.gz) and the two binary distributions 
files (xalan-j_x_x_x-bin.zip and xalan-j_x_x_x-bin.tar.gz, and xalan-j_x_x_x-bin-2jars.zip 
and xalan-j_x_x_x-bin-2jars.tar.gz).</p>
<p>Two prerequisites to signing the distribution are: 1) you must have a 
personal PGP or GPG key, and 2) the public half of your key must be in the 
appropriate KEYS file before you begin a build.  If you hadn't previously checked 
in your public key to the KEYS file before beginning this whole process, you'll 
have to go back and start again.</p>
<note>We need some good links on getting <jump href="http://web.mit.edu/network/pgp.html">PGP</jump> 
and <jump href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GPG</jump>, and on actually 
code signing and verifying signatures.  Jakarta has some, but they're 
scattered. This would be a good volunteer project for someone.</note>
<p>Sign every .zip and .tar.gz file with your personal key, and make a detached 
text file with the signature - this will usually create a 
foo.zip.asc or foo.zip.sig file for each foo.zip file you sign.</p>
<ul>
<li>Copy distros up to the website.</li>
</ul>
<p>You'll need to copy all of the distros plus all of your 
detached signature files to the website so people can download them.  Note 
that apache.org machines generally do not allow inbound ftp, so you'll need to 
either scp them or login to the apache machines and use scp or pftp from there 
outbound to some server that you've copied them to.</p>
<p>(Subject to change as www.apache.org/dist gets ready for mirroring) 
You'll need to log on to xml.apache.org (which is a separate machine 
from cvs.apache.org) and upload the files to /www/xml.apache.org/xalan-j/dist</p>
<p>You should also update the distribution directory's html files 
to note the new build numbers.  Carefully edit the .htaccess file 
to update the 'Latest Stable Build' and 'Latest Developers Build' lines  
as needed.  If you don't understand the format of this file, ask for help.</p>

</s3>



  <anchor name="doc"/>
  <s3 title="Rebuilding the &xslt4j; documentation">
    <p>&xslt4j; includes a number of XML source files, XSL stylesheets, document type definition (DTD)
      files, entity relationship (ENT) files, graphics, and a JavaScript file that provide the input for the &xslt4j;
      HTML User's Guide, and the overview and package-level documents used during the generation of Javadoc.
    </p>
    <p>
      Before rebuilding the documentation there are probably a number of pages
      that need to be updated, at a minimum consider these:
      
      <table>
        <tr><td><em>XML source file</em></td><td><em>Description of contents</em></td></tr>
        <tr><td>downloads.xml</td><td>how to download releases</td></tr>
        <tr><td>readme.xml</td><td>has the release notes for each release (most recent to the oldest release)</td></tr>
        <tr><td>whatsnew.xml</td><td>describes what is new in the latest release</td></tr>
      </table>
    <p>
      For a new release it is quite likely that some information in the
      <em>whatesnew.xml</em> page needs to be moved into the appropriate
      section of the <em>readme.xml</em> or release notes page before 
      updating both of these pages with the information for the new release.
    </p>  
    </p> 
    <p>To rebuild the documentation, you must use the StyleBook tool and the JDK 1.2.2 java and javadoc
      tools. StyleBook (which uses Xalan and Xerces) is in <code>stylebook-1.0-b2.jar</code>. Some of the document definition files,
      stylesheets, and resources are stored in xml-site-style.tar.gz, and are unzipped when you run Ant as described
       below.
    </p>
    <p>You can use Ant with the docs target to regenerate the User's Guide and with the javadocs target to regenerate the
      Javadoc API documentation.
    </p>
    <p>
      When building the Javadoc API documentation, or the HTML pages for
      the website the following Ant Targets are of interest:
    </p>
    <table>
       <tr><td><em>Ant Target</em></td><td><em>What Ant does</em></td></tr>
       <tr><td>javadocs</td><td>creates the API documentation</td></tr>
       <tr><td>serializer.javadocs</td><td>creates the API documetation for the serializer</td></tr>
       <tr><td>site</td><td>creates the HTML pages for the site http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j</td></tr>
       <tr><td>xalan.apache.org.site</td><td>creates the HTML pages for the site http://xalan.apache.org</td></tr>
  </table>
  </s3>  








<s3 title="Post-Build Docs and Email">
<p>Update the live website doc and let the community know you're done!</p>
<ul>
<li>Update website documentation set.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now that the distribution is available for downloading, you should also 
update the static copy of the documentation that's posted to xml.apache.org.  
</p>

<ul>
<li>Email xalan-dev with build notice!</li>
</ul>
<p>After everything is posted, you need to let the community know that 
a new build is available.  Write up a short email announcing this with just 
a couple of the highlights of the new build, and a link to the 
distribution area.</p>

<p>Make the subject something like:  [ANN] Xalan-J 2.x Point/Developers/Whatever Release posted to xml.apache.org
and send your email to:  general@xml.apache.org, xalan-dev@xml.apache.org, xalan-j-users@xml.apache.org.  Note 
that for developers releases, you can omit the general@xml.apache.org address if you 
don't think it will be of interest to the larger audience.
</p>
</s3>

</s2>

</s1> 
